Up until now you learn about generating a sequence of configurations
截止现在 大家学习了有关生成一系列配置的内容
for vehicle using algorithms like A* and Hybrid A*.
使用的算法是 A* 和混合 A*
We refer to this as path planning. But what about time?
有关路径规划 我们讲了这些内容 但是时间问题如何处理？
In path planning, we imagine taking
在路径规划中 我们想象着把车辆行驶的路面拿掉
our driving surface and length some sort of discretized grid on top of it.
然后把一些离散的格子放上去
Then, we make plans by specifying a start state and a goal state.
接着 我们指定开始状态和目标状态来制定规划
And the trajectories we generate looks something like this for algorithms like A*
我们使用 A* 族算法来生成这样的轨迹
or something like this for algorithms like Hybrid A*.
或者使用混合 A* 族算法来生成这样的轨迹
These algorithms play an important role in autonomous driving.
这些算法在自动驾驶中非常重要
But the path they generate don't really take predictions into account.
但是 这些算法生成路径时 并没有将预测考虑在内
For example, let's project back to when the blue vehicle first wanted to change lane.
例如 我们回到前面内容 此时蓝车想要变道
Here we will include the time as a third dimension.
这里我们会把时间纳入考量 作为第三维
One way to visualize it is to imagine looking at the road
一种可视化的方式是 想想你正在观察路面
from some angle and time would be the dimension going up.
从某个角度 时间将会是向上的维度
And one way for a vehicle to move along the path that goes around the start vehicle,
沿着道路行驶的另一辆车将会沿着某个路径绕过蓝车
would be something like that.
路径如图所示一样
The fast moving vehicle we perceived behind us is predicted to
而我们感知到的后面的快速移动车辆
move in on the lane at a fast speed which would look something like that.
预计将会高速进入这个车道 如这里所示
And that's how we know that we cannot change lane immediately.
这就是为何我们知道目前不能马上变道
If we try to go before the vehicle that passed us,
如果我们试图行驶在超过我们的车辆前方
which is another red Polygram in the two dimension.
那么从二维展示来看 我们的路径将是另一个红色四边形
We will collide with the vehicle.
那么 我们就会和该车发生碰撞
We have to wait for this vehicle to drive past us.
我们不得不等待 让该车先过去
Once the Red car has passed us,
一旦红车超过我们
we can proceed with our lane change
我们就能继续进行先前的动作
Now as you can see, having a path is nice,
现在大家都看到了 有一条路径就很不错
but it is not sufficient to solve the planning problem when there are
但是有了路径并不能完全解决规划问题 因为我们周围还有动态对象
dynamic objects around us which in autonomous driving is all the time.
在自动驾驶的世界中 动态对象时刻存在
Therefore, we have to plan not only a sequence of configuration,
因此 我们不得不不但规划一系列配置
sd and fita but also have these configurations all set up in time.
还得给这些配置赋予时间值
The trajectory is a function which for
轨迹是一个函数
any time t associates a configuration of a vehicle.
在任一时间点上 该函数可以求得一辆车的一个配置
Now, we need a way to generate such a trajectory.
现在 我们需要一种方式来生成这样的一条轨迹
And the way we're going to do this,
我们用来解决这个问题的方法
is by separating the planning we do in the S dimension,
就是把我们在 S 维度上做的规划
from the planning we do in a d dimension.
从我们在 d 维度上做的规划中分离出来
Instead of thinking about one picture in three dimension,
我们不会考虑一张三维的图片
we usually decide to reason about two pictures.
通常我们会推导出两张图片
Each of which is in two dimensions.
每一个都是2维的
I'm going to walk you through
我会给大家展示我们在上一个视频中所做的
the same vehicle tracking exercise I did in the previous video, two more times.
同样的车辆跟踪练习 我们来做两次
One for s and one for d. Let's start with s. At t=0.
一个是 s 另一个是 d 我们从 s 开始讲起
The vehicle is here at s=0.
当 t=0 时 车在这里 s=0
Then at t=1, it's here.
然后当 t=1 时 车在这里
And it keeps moving until it reaches the situation where it goes to a full stop.
该车继续行驶 直到完全停止不动
Note that we can see the vehicle has stopped by looking at this graph.
大家注意 我们可以从这张图上看出这辆车已经停下来了
Here we can see a flat slope and the flat slopes means no movement.
这里大家可以看到一个平坡 表示没有移动发生
This is something we couldn't see in that t
这在我们前面使用的 代表一条路径的t-s 关系图上
over s graph that we used before to represent a path.
是看不出来的
Then the vehicle starts moving again until it reaches its final configuration at t=15.
接着该车又开始移动 直到达到它的最终状态集 在 t=15 处
Now, let's do the same thing for d versus
现在 我们以同样的方式来查看 d 关于 t 的情况
t. As we move along the road, d remains constant.
当我们沿着道路行驶 d 保持不变
Then the vehicle goes to a full stop and after the stop, start shifting left.
接着 车辆进入完全停止状态 在停止之后 车辆开始向左位移
And after it has passed the green vehicle,
在它超过绿车之后
it goes back to its original lane.
它回到原来的车道
Finally, we can look at both trajectories
最后 我们同时来看看两条轨迹
simultaneously and the great thing is that we can
我们能够可视化地显示汽车随时间的整个运动
finally visualize the whole motion of the car over time.
这是非常方便的
It's not just a path now,
它现在不仅仅是一条路径
it's a trajectory and we can fully describe what the vehicle did within these 15 seconds.
它是一条轨迹 并且 我们可以完全描述出车辆在15秒内的动作
Next, I'm going to ask you to think about some questions involving graphs like these.
下面 我将请大家思考一些有关这些图的问题